All right, בוקר טוב Boker Tov everybody. Today's דף daf is י"א,
Yud Aleph, a short דף, daf, but I'm sure we'll find ways
to get it to take the whole hour to just talk about.
Anyway, we pick up with the... we'll just give the entire דף
יומי daf yomi through a יד, Yad, you know, I'll just say
three words and finish it out.
What? Because he would come in, have a cup of coffee and
leave?
Exactly. Okay, so we'll anyway let's quickly re-read the משנה mishna on
the bottom of י' עמוד ב' Yud Amud Bet to give us
the framing. Okay.
Now we are in the category here of like כינויים, Kinnuyim, which
is not that the sentence needs a blank to be filled in,
but you have to understand what certain words mean, you know, certain
words represent, might represent other words. So here's what the משנה mishna
says. האומר לחולין שאוכל לך, Ha'omer lachullin she'ochal lach,
which is non-חולין chullin that I will eat you, so that that
I will eat of yours is non-חולין, chullin, i.e., הקדש. Hekdesh. And
by the way, when people learn ירושלמי Yerushalmi often they get confused
because they... well, one way they get confused it's like אמר ר'
ל"א, Amar Reb Lamed Aleph, so they read it אמר רבי Amar
Rabbi or אמר רב Amar Rav לא, Lo, and it's actually רב
אילא. Rav Ila. So anyway, so that's what they... but that's a
common misreading, and another common misreading is when they have a למד
lamed at the beginning of the word they read it 'Le' and
it's really 'La', and it's a Palestinian Aramaic conjunction of non-X, you
know, or not X as one word. So לחולין. lachullin. So, האומר
לחולין שאוכל לך, Ha'omer lachullin she'ochal lach, non-חולין chullin that of yours
that that I will eat of yours, so that basically means it's
הקדש. Hekdesh. לא כשר ולא דכי, Lo kasher velo dachi, not כשר
kasher or not דכי, dachi, which is
טהור, tahor, so something after the word טהור tahor is just floating
around here so it must mean לא דהור. la d'hor. Okay, all
those things are basically words of saying that this is like a
substitute for the word קונם. Konam. So the חידוש chidush here is
that כשר kosher and טהור tahor are not necessarily opposites of the
idea of הקדש, Hekdesh, and it's not necessarily, you know, טרייף traif
and טמא tamei are not necessarily a דבר הנדור, davar hanadur, but
nevertheless we're going to interpret it that way because סתם נדרים להחמיר,
stam nedarim l'hachmir, if it has sort of ambiguous meaning, we'll give
it the more stricter meaning and you can use the word, you
know, not כשר kosher or טמא tamei to signify a status of
a קרבן. korban. More explicitly is the next set of phrases: טמא
נותר ופיגול אסור. Tamei notar u'pigul asur. So טמא, tamei, נותר notar
and פיגול, pigul, so נותר notar and פיגול pigul only happen by
קרבנות, korbanot, טמא tamei can happen by other things, but all of
those and it seems... it refers to a status of a קרבן
korban and therefore you're making something like a קרבן. korban.
Again, it could have other possible meanings, טמא tamei could mean something
else, נותר notar and פיגול pigul might not mean that you want...
may mean actually the איסור issur of נותר, notar, not like the
הקדש Hekdesh status of the קרבן korban of that is נותר, notar,
right? And so it has to still be by a דבר הנדור
davar hanadur and that's how we're going to interpret it, even though
it's possible other meanings. כאימרא, Ke'imra, כדירים, kedirim, כעצים, ke'etzim, if you
say like sheep, like the pens, like wood, כאישים ke'ishim or like
the fires on the altar, כמזבח, ke'mizbeach, כהיכל, ke'heichal, כירושלים. ke'yerushalayim. All
those things, now those are not דבר הנדור, davar hanadur, I mean
well maybe you can be נודר noder sheep, you're not נודר noder
the pens, you're not... you could be נודר noder wood which is
presumably... you're not exactly נודר noder ירושלים, Yerushalayim, it's not a דבר
הנדור, davar hanadur, they do have קדושה kedusha or they are associated
with the idea of קרבנות, korbanot, so all of those are interpreted
as ways of saying the idea of קרבן. korban. In all of
those things, נדר באחד מכל המשמשים מזבח neder be'achad mikol hameshamshim mizbeach
or anything that is used in the מזבח, mizbeach, אף על פי
שלא הזכיר קרבן, af al pi shelo hizkir korban, even though you
don't say קרבן, korban, הרי זה נדר בקרבן. harei zeh neder be'korban.
That is, it works for קרבן. korban. רבי יהודה אומר האומר ירושלים
לא אמר כלום. Rabbi Yehudah Omer Ha'Omer Yerushalayim Lo Amar Klum. To
say ירושלים, Yerushalayim, it's meaningless. The question is, is he saying that
even if you say כירושלים Ke'yerushalayim it's meaningless, and that ירושלים Yerushalayim
refers to like the city and that's not seen as there's so
many other things that are part of ירושלים Yerushalayim other than קרבנות
korbanot and the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, so maybe it's not seen
as a substitute for the word קרבן, korban, or is it the
difference between saying ירושלים Yerushalayim and כירושלים? Ke'yerushalayim?
And that we'll sort of explore in the גמרא. Gemara. Yes, Michael?
I'm just trying to understand something. Shouldn't it... it might be a
misunderstanding, shouldn't it have just said לא טהור lo tahor instead?
Yeah, I said that. I said something after the word טהור, tahor,
some have the גירסא girsa לא טהור, lo tahor, the word טהור
tahor here is funny in the משנה. mishna. Okay, let's take a
look at the גמרא Gemara now, top of י"א עמוד א'. Yud
Aleph Amud Aleph. סברוה, Savruah, we're assuming that מאי לחולין, mai lachullin,
what does לחולין lachullin mean? לא לחולין להוי, Lo lechullin lehavei, this
should not be considered חולין chullin אלא קרבן, ela korban, it should
be a קרבן, korban, and therefore that which I eat from you
is not חולין, chullin, meaning that which I eat from you is
a קרבן korban and it's אסור. asur. Okay, so הא מן... ha
man... אלא קרבן, ela korban, מני מתניתין? mani matnissin? Who is our
משנה? mishna? אי רבי מאיר, Ie Rabbi Meir, if it's רבי מאיר,
Rabbi Meir, לית ליה מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן. leis lei mikh'lal
lav ata shomei'a hen. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir doesn't say that just
because somebody says not X it's the opposite is inferred. דתנן, De'tnan,
we taught in the משנה, mishna, רבי מאיר אומר כל תנאי שאינו
כתנאי בני גד ובני ראובן אינו תנאי. Rabbi Meir omer kol tnai
she'eino k'tnai b'nei gad u'b'nei reuven eino tnai.
Any תנאי tnai that's not like the condition of בני גד ובני
ראובן B'nei Gad u'B'nei Reuven is not a תנאי. tnai. What did
בני גד ובני ראובן B'nei Gad u'B'nei Reuven say? If they will
pass over with you, then they will inherit on this side of
the Jordan, and if they don't pass over with you, then they
won't inherit on this side of the Jordan and they'll inherit
ארץ... Eretz... Otherwise we can't say that from saying yes you can
infer no or no you can infer yes. So since רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir says you have to say both sides, it's not enough
to say לא חולין lo chullin what I will eat from you
means that what I eat from you is considered a קרבן. korban.
Now let's take out a moment and understand what רבי מאיר Rebbi
Meir is saying and the logic behind it. So one point could
be, he could say, look, it's obviously very clear what you mean.
Nobody suggests that if you say if A then B, that you
mean if not A then not B. But nevertheless, you have to
say it, right? And if you have to say it when you
make a stipulation and a condition, and you have to say it
maybe when you make a נדר, neder, it goes back to like
discussions we had before about יד yad and speech acts and so
on. Maybe if it was just a question of your דעת, da'as,
you wouldn't have to say it. Okay, but it's not just a
question of your דעת. da'as. One thing to appreciate about a תנאי
tnai is that a תנאי tnai is not just a question of
like, oh, under those circumstances I never would have done it. Right?
A תנאי tnai is like an artificial device. Meaning, a תנאי tnai
is different than דעת. da'as. Like, this gets into a whole discussion.
But let's say basically, I don't know, somebody sold something to someone
because, you know, he thought that the story in the גמרא Gemara
is he was planning on making עליה, aliyah, so he sold his
house, and then it turned out he couldn't make עליה, aliyah, so
then the whole sale is like void. Okay, so he didn't make
a תנאי, tnai, everybody says. He didn't make a תנאי כפול, tnai
kaful, he didn't say anything, it was just his דעת. da'as. Okay,
but that was fundamental to his state of mind. He never would
have entered into the agreement had he like, you know, had he
realized that he wasn't going to be able to make עליה. aliyah.
As opposed to a תנאי, tnai, which is like, okay, if the
Yankees win the World Series, this will take effect, and if not,
it won't take effect. Right? Where
fundamentally we assume you really have a דעת da'as to do it,
you're just creating some external mechanism that is going to like interrupt
the effect of it under certain conditions. But it's not like it's
central to your דעת. da'as. So that's creating this type of that
requires maybe very particular rules of how do you formulate it to
create this type of a mechanism. The same way by a נדר
neder we've been saying that it's not just a question of what's
in your mind, it's a question about what you actually said, there's
a speech act, and it might need very particular ways to be
formulated. So one way of understanding what רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir is
saying is there's no question what you mean, but there's a question
about what you said. And just because you said if A then
B, you did not say if not A then not B. So
that's one way of understanding רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. Another way, however,
of understanding him is that, no, there actually is a logical gap.
You're actually, for everybody who remembers their propositional logic from high school
or college, if A then B does not mean if not A
then not B, right? If it rains, I'll give you ten dollars.
If it doesn't rain, maybe I'll also give you ten dollars. Maybe
I'll give you twenty dollars. Right? And who says that it means
if it doesn't rain I won't give you ten dollars? If, right,
if P then Q, you know, the only thing that's inferable from
if P then Q? If not Q then not P. If it
rains, I'll give you ten dollars. So if I didn't give you
ten dollars, it must mean it didn't rain, right? Because had it
rained, I would have given you ten dollars. Okay, but it doesn't
mean that if it doesn't rain, I won't give you ten dollars.
You know, who knows what I'm going to do if it doesn't
rain. So therefore, if you say, right, if בני ראובן בני גד
Bnei Reuven Bnei Gad if cross over, you know, then they'll get
what they asked for in עבר הירדן, Ever HaYarden, and if they
didn't cross over, then they'll get that and a million dollars. Who
knows? Then they'll get half of that. Who knows what will happen?
Right? It doesn't mean necessarily that
then that if מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן, miklal lav ata shome'a
hen, מכלל הן אתה שומע לאו. miklal hen ata שומע לאו. Now,
again, what רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir might be saying is is that,
okay, maybe if you asked me deep down do I really know
what you meant? Yes, of course I know you meant if not
P then not Q because you said if P then Q. But
again, because logically it's not necessitated by your words, then therefore you
did not say what was needed to be said, okay? If you
need if there's a meaning combine the two ideas. There's a need
for a formal speech act. It doesn't mean that everything has to
be explicit. Okay, but here you said if P then Q, maybe
we know you mean if not P then not Q, but since
you didn't say that and since it's not logically derivable from what
you said because logically that statement could mean even if not P
then, you know, doesn't mean necessarily the reverse. So therefore, you didn't
say it. And if you didn't say it, it doesn't work as
a תנאי, tnai, you didn't say it, it doesn't work as a
נדר. neder. That's רבי מאיר's Rebbi Meir position. And therefore, if you
say לא חולין אוכל לך, lo chullin ochal lach, you cannot necessarily
infer that it is קרבן korban what I will eat from you.
Now what do you want to say?
You're using this as an example, though. Doesn't the תורה Torah explicitly
say that if they don't cross over then they go to get
their inheritance in the land?
Yes, but it says both parts of it.
That's רבי מאיר's Rebbi Meir point. Why did it have to say
both parts? parts? Just say, if you go over, you'll get the
inheritance on עבר ירדן. Ever Yarden. It says, and if they don't
go over, then they won't get their inheritance on עבר ירדן, Ever
Yarden, then they'll get it in the land. Why did it have
to say both parts? To show you that just saying one part
you're not allowed to infer the second part. Okay?
So that's what the גמרא Gemara says. So it sounds like our
משנה Mishnah is
not רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Now, I have to tell you though,
that this case in the משנה Mishnah is not necessarily work consistent
part of this idea of מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן, michellal lav
atah shome'a hen, which תוספות Tosafot points out a little later in
the סוגיא, sugya, and תוספות רי"ד Tosafot Rid even makes a bigger
point about it. Because if I say that thing of yours is
not
חולין, chulin, okay? So,
I'm not saying, if I say, here's an example of רבי מאיר,
Rabbi Meir, okay,
the things I will eat from you, everything other than this loaf
of bread is חולין. chulin. So therefore from that maybe we should
infer the things I will eat from you is חולין, chulin, so
we should infer that this thing here is not חולין, chulin, okay?
Is הקדש. hekdesh. That's like מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן. michellal lav
atah shome'a hen. Not necessarily, it is also
חולין, chulin, because there's a logical jump.
I didn't say, it's because it could be חולין.
chulin. Right, no, but even assuming, fine, yes, exactly, it could also
be חולין. chulin. Everything else is חולין chulin and this is חולין.
chulin. Okay, right. But I'm wanting to say it's not just that
there's other possibilities other than non-חולין, chulin, but it's also that even
if maybe it also is חולין, chulin, right. Okay, that would be
רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Everything else is חולין, chulin, and so then
I'm supposed to infer that this is not חולין. chulin. Maybe I
can't infer that. But here no, I'm saying this object itself is
not חולין. chulin. Okay, so what is it? So it's something other
than חולין. chulin. Now, if the only thing that exists other than
חולין, chulin, let's say I said not
קרבן, korban, this object, no, not חולין. chulin. Not a non-קרבן, korban,
let's assume that the only thing other than חולין chulin is קרבן,
korban, because I think that
that's not part of his מכלל לאו. michellal lav. This thing is
not חולין. chulin. So what is it? It's קרבן. korban. Okay? So
meaning, it's not מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן. michellal lav atah shome'a
hen. I'm describing it as not X.
Not X is Y, so
what is it if it's not X? It's something else. Tautology? Right,
it's so therefore right, it's not if this happens then this. That's
מכלל לאו. michellal lav. If this then this, so if not this,
then I don't know. But I'm saying no, there actually is something,
what is it? It's something other than חולין. chulin. So it sounds
like I'm saying that it's a קרבן. korban. So anyway, so that's
why some ראשונים, rishonim, particularly the תוספות רי"ד, Tosafot Rid, says that
when the גמרא Gemara begins this by saying סברוה, savruha, we're assuming
that this is part of the idea of מכלל לאו אתה שומע
הן, michellal lav atah shome'a hen, and this doesn't work according to
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, that ultimately we're going to reject that idea.
Now the problem is that the גמרא Gemara isn't clear at what
stage it rejects it. Maybe תוספות רי"ד Tosafot Rid says it's when
we get to the עמוד ב׳, amud bet, and you'll see what
we discuss when we get to the עמוד ב׳. amud bet. So
the תוספות רי"ד Tosafot Rid actually says in the end this is
completely unrelated to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Even if you say מכלל
לאו אתה שומע הן, michellal lav atah shome'a hen, when you're saying
this thing is not חולין, chulin, you're saying that it's הקדש. hekdesh.
Okay?
But nevertheless, at this stage, the גמרא Gemara is working with the
idea that this is tied into רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. So if
this is going to work, this thing is not חולין, chulin, i.e.
הקדש, hekdesh, that's if you, at least at this stage, the גמרא
Gemara says, don't reject רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, and say מכלל לאו
אתה שומע הן. michellal lav atah shome'a hen. Okay?
Yes, so what to me what the גמרא Gemara is doing is
there's a rhetorical shift, because the whole concept of יד yad or
ידיים yadayim is more about literary ellipsis and context and meaning that
are clearly suggested. They're not tightly argued logical
statements. So the גמרא Gemara is playing with two different dimensions of
language: a rhetorical dimension of language and a logical positivist dimension of
language.
Right. I think it's an interesting way of thinking about it. Yeah,
I hear that. I hear you. I hear. It's an interesting way
of thinking about it. Look, the other point to be made just
is the difference between a יד yad and a כינוי. kinuy. A
יד yad basically says we're going to fill in the blanks. A
כינוי kinuy basically says there are no blanks. It was a full
sentence, but we have to interpret what particular words mean. So, and
to interpret what particular words mean it becomes more of a technical
question. קונם konam means something. מכנמנא michnamna doesn't mean that. Okay, who
cares if מכנמנא michnamna is not a כינוי kinuy for the word
קרבן? korban? Isn't it still clear what you wanted to do? Let's
employ the idea of יד, yad, right? So what seems to happen
is, is that יד yad is when there's a blank that needs
to be filled in. כינוי kinuy is when all of the pieces
of the sentence are there, but we have to interpret what the
individual words mean, and then for, and then we become a little
bit more technical in that process.
Okay. No, it seems
to be
כינוי. Kinui. Well, if you said, right, right, that's a good point,
meaning, if you say לחולין, LaChullin, that sounds like כינוי. Kinui. That
לחולין LaChullin is a word that means קרבן, Korban, okay. If you
basically said something is, you know, this is like the the they
sometimes do that, right? This is like the
unbutter. Yeah, whatever, I don't know, something like that. Yeah, this is
like unbutter or something like that, you know? It's a way of
saying that it's something else, so then you could say that that
actually is כינוי. Kinui. But if you were to say the thing
that the גמרא Gemara sort of is imagining you're saying, that everything
else other than this is
חולין, Chullin, you know, and and then I'm supposed to therefore assume
that this is not חולין, Chullin, then yeah, then that's more of
a יד Yad than a כינוי, Kinui, I would agree. But in
the משנה, Mishnah, but that's why it's funny to put it into
the idea of מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן, Michlal Lav Atah Shomeia
Hein, because really that's not what's happening. What's happening is you are
describing this thing and using a funny term to describe it. This
thing is non-חולין. Chullin. And therefore it really is כינוי. Kinui. You
refer to the object, you had a full sentence, you said all
the words. We have to say, what does the word non-חולין Chullin
mean? So that is כינוי, Kinui, right? It's a what does this
phrase mean? Does this phrase equal to the word קונם, Konam, the
word קרבן? Korban?
Well before when we were talking about כינוי, Kinui, we didn't we
didn't bring up the subject of מכלל לאו אתה
שומע הן.
Michlal Lav
Atah Shomeia Hein. I understand. That's what I'm trying to make, that
it looks to me like this is a category of comparison rather
than naming something a certain way.
Well, I think that's where the גמרא Gemara is taking it, but
I don't think that's my point is I don't think that's what
the משנה Mishnah says. When the משנה Mishnah says things like
טמא נותר פיגול, Tamei Notar Pigul, כאימרא כדירים כעצים כאישים, Ke'Imra Kedirim
Ke'Eitzin Ke'Ishim, clearly it's dealing with a type of קונם, Konam, not
a of of כינוי Kinui of a
derivation of the word קרבן, Korban, which was our first step of
כינוי, Kinui, קונם קונס קונח, Konam Konas Konach, but a word that
is standing as a stand-in for the word
קרבן, Korban, כעצים כאישים כירושלים. Ke'Eitzin Ke'Ishim KiYerushalayim. That's a stand-in word
for קרבן. Korban. So טמא נותר פיגול Tamei Notar Pigul is a
stand-in word for קרבן. Korban. That's what a כינוי Kinui is, okay?
So לחולין LaChullin presumably is a stand-in word for קרבן. Korban. It's
very straightforward, right? The fact that the גמרא Gemara introduces מכלל לאו
אתה שומע הן Michlal Lav Atah Shomeia Hein is strange, which is
why the תוספות Tosafot says that in the end we reject it.
That's what the word סברוה Savruha here means. Okay, so let's keep
on going. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says אלא רבי יהודה היא. Ela Rabbi Yehudah
Hi. So therefore if לחולין LaChullin is supposed to mean קרבן, Korban,
it's רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah that says מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן.
Michlal Lav Atah Shomeia Hein. אימא סיפא, Eima Seifa, but look at
the end of the משנה. Mishnah. רבי יהודה אומר האומר ירושלים לא
אמר כלום. Rabbi Yehudah Omer Ha'Omer Yerushalayim Lo Amar Klum. So if
you say ירושלים, Yerushalayim, it doesn't count. מדסיפא רבי יהודה רישא לאו
רבי יהודה. MiDeSeifa Rabbi Yehudah Reisha Lav Rabbi Yehudah. So since the
end of the משנה Mishnah is רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehudah, clearly this
משנה Mishnah is not רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehudah.
And therefore we're back to square one. If it's רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Meir, then how does לחולין LaChullin mean קרבן? Korban? So the גמרא
Gemara says no, כולה רבי יהודה היא. Kulah Rabbi Yehudah Hi. No,
it's all רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehudah. והכי קתני, VeHachi Katani, רבי יהודה
אומר Rabbi Yehuda omer האומר ירושלים לא אמר כלום. ha'omer Yerushalayim lo
amar klum. So therefore no, it's all רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah and
therefore when רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah says ירושלים Yerushalayim doesn't it doesn't
work, he's not arguing with the earlier part of the משנה. Mishnah.
The earlier part of the משנה Mishnah said כירושלים KiYerushalayim works. ירושלים
Yerushalayim doesn't work, okay?
So therefore and it's all רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehudah, okay? So now
the question is when do you need the כ Ke and when
do you not need the כ? Ke? So I mentioned this yesterday,
the ר״ן Ran says if you say something like פיגול נותר טמא,
Pigul Notar Tamei, which is actually a status of the thing, קונם
קונס קונח, Konam Konas Konach, that actually is describing the thing itself
as a דבר הנדור Davar HaNadur and actually like highlighting, foregrounding its
איסור Issur
status, right? פיגול נותר טמא Pigul Notar Tamei etc. קונם. Konam. So
you don't need the כ, Ke, okay? But if I say this
is מזבח, Mizbeiach, this is ירושלים, Yerushalayim, this is אימרא, Imra, so
even if it's clear that what I'm getting at is things that
are offered on the מזבח Mizbeiach and so on, right, because I
am not actually saying it, because it's like it's not the thing
itself, it's something associated with the thing and its identity as a
דבר אסור Davar Assur is not being foregrounded, there I need the
כ. Ke. And if I don't say it with the כ, Ke,
my sentence is a lot less meaningful, right? If I you understand
this, if I say this is ירושלים, Yerushalayim, what the heck does
that mean? If it's כירושלים, KiYerushalayim, like ירושלים, Yerushalayim, oh, like the
way ירושלים Yerushalayim is associated with קרבנות Korbanot and a דבר נדור
Davar Nadur whatever, this is like this is the מזבח. Mizbeiach. It
isn't a מזבח Mizbeiach and a מזבח, Mizbeiach, this is a sheep,
right? It doesn't mean anything. But this is like a sheep, you're
then associating it with a certain idea of the sheep, a sheep
sometimes is a קרבן Korban and with that status of a קרבן
Korban is what you're associating with and and so on. So so
that's what he says, that's why you need the כ. Ke. If
you say something that itself is קרבן Korban or a status of
a קרבן, Korban, פגול, Pigul, נותר, Nosar, טמא, Tomei, and foregrounds its
halachic identity, okay, then you don't need the כ, Ki, but here
you do, and that's why the end of the משנה Mishna has
all the כ. Ki. And what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is just
saying is without the כ Ki it doesn't work. ירושלים Yerushalayim works,
I mean כי ירושלים Ki Yerushalayim works, but ירושלים Yerushalayim does not
work. Okay, so that's how the whole משנה Mishna is רבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yehuda. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this:
One minute, if that's what you're saying that the difference is whether
you say the כ Ki or not, וכי קאמר כי ירושלים רבי
יהודה מי מיתסר? Vachi Ka'amar Ki Yerushalayim Rabbi Yehuda Mi Meitser? So
if you say כי ירושלים Ki Yerushalayim are you telling me for
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda it really is אסור? Assur? והתניא, Vehatanya, we
taught in a ברייתא, Braisa, רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda Omer, האומר
כי ירושלים לא אמר כלום. Ha'omer Ki Yerushalayim Lo Amar Klum. If
you say כי ירושלים Ki Yerushalayim it doesn't work, עד שידור בדבר
הקרב בירושלים. Ad Sheyidor Bidvar Hakorev Biyerushalayim.
You have to say something offered in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. ירושלים Yerushalayim itself
doesn't directly associate with other things: מזבח, Mizbeach, sheep, pens of sheep,
wood, those are things that clearly are directly associated with things that
are brought on the מזבח. Mizbeach. But ירושלים, Yerushalayim, I mean, you
know, there's a lot of things in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, right?
There's the כנסת Knesset and there's museums and there's the Biblical Zoo
and there's like a lot of things that are in ירושלים Yerushalayim
that are not directly associated with קרבנות. Korbanot. So just saying ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, even if you say כי ירושלים, Ki Yerushalayim, doesn't necessarily do
it.
Okay. The zoo, I think you said.
Oh, there you go, because of the sheep in the zoo. Okay,
so anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says לא אמר כלום, Lo Amar Klum,
עד שידור בדבר הקרב בירושלים. Ad Sheyidor Bidvar Hakorev Biyerushalayim. So the
גמרא Gemara says fine, כולה רבי יהודה היא, Kula Rabbi Yehuda Hi,
we're still going to insist what we said, no, the whole משנה
Mishna is רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, and in the משנה Mishna רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda does make a difference between ירושלים Yerushalayim and כי
ירושלים. Ki Yerushalayim. כי ירושלים Ki Yerushalayim actually would work according to
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, but תרי תנאי אליבא דרבי יהודה, Trei Tannai
Aliba DeRabbi Yehuda, that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that you quoted in
the ברייתא Braisa that says even כי ירושלים Ki Yerushalayim doesn't work
is a different תנא. Tanna. Okay, so basically we have two ways
of reading רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda in the משנה. Mishna. Either רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says כי ירושלים Ki Yerushalayim I agree works, ירושלים
Yerushalayim does not, and if you read it that way רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda could be the entire author of the משנה, Mishna, and
that deals with our מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן Michlal Lav Ata
Shomeia Hen issue. And the alternative is to say that no, that
the end of the משנה, Mishna, that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda actually
says even כי ירושלים Ki Yerushalayim is no good, and that the
beginning of the משנה Mishna is not רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, but
that's a problem for us. So we're choosing to say the whole
משנה Mishna is רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda actually
does make a distinction between the כי ירושלים Ki Yerushalayim and ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, and the ברייתא Braisa is a different approach within רבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yehuda. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, turning
to the עמוד ב, Amud Beis,
תניא, Tanya, תנא ברייתא: Tana Braisa:
חולין, Chulin, החולין, Hachulin, כחולין. Kachulin. Okay, so all those words are
חולין, Chulin, those are not words of קונם, Konam, those are all
what you, right? So בין שאוכל לך בין שלא אוכל לך, Bein
She'ochel Lach Bein Shelo Ochel Lach, whether you say that of yours
that I will eat is חולין, Chulin, whether you say, okay, שכוח,
Shkoach, it's חולין, Chulin, you didn't say anything. Or you say that
of yours which I will not eat is חולין, Chulin, which therefore
this is a real
מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן. Michlal Lav Ata Shomeia Hen. Anything of
yours that is not edible is חולין. Chulin. So then you could
say: Oh, what are you saying? Are you saying that those things
of mine, everything of yours that isn't food is חולין? Chulin? Okay,
so then you could say: Ah, what are you trying to say?
You're trying to say that the thing that is food is a
קרבן, Korban, right? You see, that's a מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן.
Michlal Lav Ata Shomeia Hen. Everything of yours that's not food is
חולין. Chulin. So then that could say food is a קרבן. Korban.
That might be a מכלל לאו. Michlal Lav. Nevertheless, מותר, Mutar, it's
not a problem. Why? Because presumably we say רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir,
מכלל לאו אי אתה שומע הן. Michlal Lav I Ata Shomeia Hen.
Everybody with me? So if you say your food is חולין, Chulin,
obviously you said nothing. If you say your non-food is חולין, Chulin,
then you want to say, so your non-food, everything that's not food
is חולין, Chulin, so that sounds like everything that is food is
קרבן, Korban, nevertheless we don't say that, מכלל לאו אי אתה שומע
הן, Michlal Lav I Ata Shomeia Hen, this is רבי מאיר. Rabbi
Meir. Okay. מותר. Mutar. לחולין שאוכל לך אסור. Lachulin She'ochel Lach Assur.
But לחולין, Lachulin, the thing, the food of yours, those things that
I would eat of yours, your food is לחולין, Lachulin, that's forbidden.
Now why? Right? Why? Your food is לחולין, Lachulin, non-חולין Chulin is
forbidden, is because non-חולין Chulin means קרבן. Korban. Everybody with me here?
So that sounds like מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן. Michlal Lav Ata
Shomeia Hen. That if I say your stuff is non-חולין, Chulin, it
works, that's מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן. Michlal Lav Ata Shomeia Hen.
So here's where the תוספות רי"ד Tosafot Rid says, this is where
we reject what we were assuming on the עמוד א. Amud Alef.
Here clearly this משנה Mishna is רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, this ברייתא
Braisa is רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. This ברייתא Braisa assumes that if
you say
your non-food is חולין Chulin we don't interpret it to mean that
your food is קרבן, Korban, מכלל לאו אי אתה שומע הן, Michlal
Lav I Ata Shomeia Hen, and nevertheless when you say your food
is לחולין Lachulin is non-חולין, Chulin, non-חולין Chulin is just a word
for קרבן, Korban, so that even רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir can accept
the position that לחולין Lachulin is a word for קרבן. Korban.
Is that because it can't be anything else? Is that why?
No, not because it can't be anything else, because you're not saying
a conditional statement. It's a synonym. You're not saying a conditional statement.
If I say... You know, you are
you are impure. Here's a good example. If I say you're impure,
does that mean oh one minute, so you're basically saying that I'm
טמא tamei but that's only if you hold like רבי מאיר Rebbe
Meir that מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן? mikhallal lav atah shomeia hen?
Because impure means not pure, so I have to say not pure
means טמא. tamei. Oh, that's only if you say מכלל לאו. mikhallal
lav. No! I said you're impure, that's טמא, tamei, okay? I said
you're לחולין, lachullin, לחולין lachullin is קרבן, korban, right? Right? That's what
the word... if I say you're invincible, it means that you're invincible.
It doesn't mean you're not vincible and therefore you are, wait, what
are you? Oh, מכלל לאו. mikhallal lav. The word non-x is just
a way of saying the opposite word. It's not a logical... right.
So therefore that's what the תוספות ריד Tosafos Rid says, that at
this stage לחולין lachullin just means קרבן korban and it's not a
logical proposition that you have to infer the reverse, okay? And therefore
he says and this is where we assume it, that the beginning
is clearly רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir because the logical idea of רבי
מאיר Rebbe Meir is your non-food is
חולין. chullin. Your non-food is חולין. chullin. And the reverse would be
your food is not חולין. chullin. That is we don't say that's
מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן. mikhallal lav atah shomeia hen.
So really the משנה mishna could be רבי מאיר. Rebbe Meir.
That's exactly what the תוספות ריד Tosafos Rid says. The משנה mishna
is רבי מאיר, Rebbe Meir, okay? So that's where the תוספות ריד
Tosafos Rid says that we reverse ourselves. Now by the way, just
to show you the inventiveness of the other ראשונים rishonim who say
we don't reverse ourselves, so how do they, if they say this
ברייתא braisa here is רבי מאיר, Rebbe Meir, how do they deal
with the idea that לחולין lachullin is אסור, assur, right? So they
have two possible interpretations. One is they say in this in this
phrase you're not saying לחולין, lachullin, you're saying לחולין. lichullin.
So that's why it's אסור. assur.
So then why would you conclude that the משנה mishna is according
to רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir if you if we reject the idea
that it's a logical construct, it's just definitional, right?
That's what the תוספות ריד Tosafos Rid says. That's not what the
other ראשונים rishonim say. The other ראשונים rishonim say that the same
way the גמרא Gemara framed this as a מכלל לאו, mikhallal lav,
it's consistent, right?
That allows the משנה mishna to say it's not according to רבי
מאיר Rebbe Meir then, right? Right. And why do you say תוספות
ריד, Tosafos Rid, this was תוספות? Tosafos?
Because I'm not quoting this תוספות, Tosafos, I'm quoting a separate ספר
sefer that's called the תוספות ריד, Tosafos Rid, yeah, exactly, okay. So
how do you deal with this? So he says that oh
I'm sorry, לחולין לא אוכל לך lachullin lo okhal lekha, wouldn't work
either. Because anyway some say he just crosses out that sentence. That's
one way of dealing with the problem. And the other way is
the ראב"ד's Raavad answer. The ראב"ד's Raavad answer is he takes out
the ו. vav. So he doesn't read it as לחולין לא אוכל
לך, lachullin lo ochal lach but he reads לחלין לא אוכל לך,
lechallin lo
okhal lekha, חלות תודה. challos todah.
So therefore it's instead talking about חלות תודה. challos todah. Everything else
was talking about חולין, chullin, this phrase is talking about חלות תודה.
challos todah. Obviously a very very forced read, okay. So this is
really a very pushes, anyway logically the תוספות ריד Tosafos Rid is
totally correct, right? It's very bizarre the הוה אמינא hava amina of
the גמרא, Gemara, you know, one that to think that this is
part of מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן. mikhallal lav atah shomeia hen.
This is just the word that describes this object. To describe something
as non-חולין chullin is to say just like I said, perfect example,
to describe it as impure is to say that it's טמא. tamei.
To describe it as לחולין lichullin is to say that it's קרבן.
korban. Okay, so we're going to read it like the תוספות ריד.
Tosafos Rid. So if you say, if you say your non-food is
חולין, chullin, it does not mean that your food is קרבן. korban.
But if you say your food is non-חולין, chullin, then that is
אסור. assur. That is a language of קרבן. korban. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this, לחולין לא אוכל לך מותר. lachullin
lo okhal lekha mutar. It says רישא מני? רבי מאיר היא. reisha
manni Rebbe Meir hi. So the beginning is רישא. reisha.
I'm sorry, I forgot the last phrase. So then you have, so
the לחולין שאוכל לך אסור, lachullin she-okhal lekha assur,
that's the proof of the תוספות ריד. Tosafos Rid. That means this
is non-חולין, chullin, this is a קרבן, korban, and therefore it's אסור.
assur. לחולין לא אוכל לך מותר. lachullin lo okhal lekha mutar.
Non-חולין chullin what I won't eat from you, then it's מותר mutar
because then you're saying because you're saying, you know, you're not so
we'll see that, but obviously you're not saying the food is לחולין,
lachullin so therefore it's going to be מותר. mutar. Okay, רישא מני
reisha manni? רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir היא. hi. Our beginning is רישא.
reisha. דלית ליה מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן. de-leit leih mikhallal lav
atah shomeia hen. He doesn't say מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן, mikhallal
lav atah shomeia hen, right? Because what's the proof for that? That's
the phrase of... okay, let's see what's the three statements in the
משנה, mishna, okay? So one is חולין לא אוכל לך. chullin lo
okhal lekha.
That's the רישא. reisha. The middle case is לחולין שאוכל לך, lachullin
she-okhal lekha, שאוכל
לך. she-okhal lekha. This
is
מותר, mutar,
אסור, assur,
מותר.
mutar. לחולין לא אוכל לך אסור? lachullin lo okhal lekha assur?
Yeah, I'm the food. You're saying it on a piece of bread.
Okay, so it's not חולין. chullin.
Right, so that's why it's what minute... so חולין לא אוכל לך
chullin lo okhal lekha is מותר, mutar, right? Because that means this
is the מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן. mikhallal lav atah shomeia hen.
Okay, here's my food, okay, here's my apple. That's the, you know,
that's basically the שאוכל לך, she-okhal lekha, things of yours I would
eat. So לא אוכל לך, lo okhal lekha I don't know, that's
my house.
Don't you love my pictures? Okay, anyway.
So how do you get inside?
This can mean one of two things. This can either mean like
a שבועה *shevuah*, חולין *Chulin*, I won't eat your stuff. That doesn't
mean—whatever—maybe we could talk about whether that's a שבועה *shevuah*.
Are you talking to
a direct address?
Right, right. No, it's like a—I
don't know, it's like a—it's like an—expletive—no,
not explicative—im—not imperative—impre—anyway, there's some other word for—anyway. Expletive? Anyway, no, I
was thinking about another word, it's like a—anyway, okay, okay,
inter—anyway, moving on. Okay, so that would mean nothing. Now if you're
talking about an object, you're saying that that I won't eat of
yours, things that are non-food are חולין *Chulin*. Okay, your house is
חולין *Chulin*, you know, your car and house are חולין *Chulin*. So
does that mean that my food is הקדש heckdesh. *hekdesh*? That would
be מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן miklal lav ata shomei hen, *miklal
lav attah shomea hen*. So by saying it's מותר mutar, *mutar*, we're
saying that that's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, *Rabbi Meir*. You do not
say that just because this is חולין *Chulin*, right, therefore that's הקדש
heckdesh, *hekdesh*. You don't say that. מכלל לאו אי אתה שומע הן
*miklal lav ee attah shomea hen* and it's מותר mutar *mutar*. That's
that, okay. That proves that we're רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir*.
This part is the part the גמרא gemara, *Gemara* like leapfrogs over
and ignores. And this is the part that the תוספות רי"ד Tosafot
Rid, *Tosafot Rid* says that this word לחולין lachullin, *Lachulin* just is
another way of saying הקדש heckdesh, *hekdesh*, right? I think a good
example is my example of saying 'impure equals טמא *tamei*'. That's not
מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן *miklal lav attah shomea hen*, that's just
what the word means. So even though רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* says
that just because you say 'this is not חולין *Chulin*' doesn't mean
that this is—that this is חולין *Chulin* doesn't mean this is הקדש
heckdesh, *hekdesh*. Okay, fine. We don't infer from—from, you know, this to
that. This isn't inferring. This is just saying the food is הקדש
heckdesh, *hekdesh*, the apples are הקדש heckdesh, *hekdesh*, אסור assur. *assur*. Okay,
now we're going to have to worry about what this means. Okay,
now this basically
means—so this—I mean this should obviously like be מותר mutar *mutar*. If
לחולין לא אוכל לך lachullin lo ochal lach *Lachulin lo ochal lach*,
that means your house and your car are non-חולין *Chulin*.
So, of course it's מותר mutar? *mutar*. You haven't said anything about
my food. Even when you said my house and my car are
חולין *Chulin*, we don't say מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן *miklal lav
attah shomea hen*. So this certainly should be מותר *mutar*. Okay, so
we're going to have to figure out that last phrase, but if
this is מותר *mutar*, then this certainly should be מותר *mutar*.
A way of saying this is now הקדש heckdesh *hekdesh*.
So let's take a look.
לא אוכל לך lo okhal lekha, *Lo ochal lach* means loosely that
I normally would not eat from you?
Yeah, those things of yours that I won't eat, let's say. Okay,
or it could be לשון lashon שבועה *lashon shevuah*. חולין *Chulin*, like—like,
you know, 'that I won't eat from you'. But then it's like—then
we have to worry about that as a type of a שבועה
*shevuah*. Let's take a look at the גמרא gemara *Gemara*. Okay, so
הגמרא *the Gemara* says like this: מאני *Mani*—okay, רישא מאני רבי מאיר
היא דלית ליה מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן *Reisha mani? Rabbi Meir
hi, d'leit lei miklal lav attah shomea hen*. אימא סיפא לחולין lachullin,
לא אוכל לך lo ochal lach מותר והתנן *Eima seifa: Lachulin lo
ochal lach, mutar.
Vehatnan*—now that normally would make total sense, as we said. It's a
silly statement, right? At most, you know, even if you say חולין
לא אוכל לך lo ochal lach *Chulin lo ochal lach* it's מותר
*mutar*, certainly לחולין lachullin לא אוכל לך lo ochal lach *Lachulin lo
ochal lach* should be מותר *mutar*. But then גמרא gemara. *Gemara* says
one minute, והתנן *vehatnan*, we have a later משנה mishnah *Mishnah* coming
up which is a רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* position that says לקרבן
לא אוכל לך lekorban lo ochal lach רבי מאיר אוסר *Lakurban lo
ochal lach, Rabbi Meir osser*. That if you say לקרבן לא אוכל
לך le-korban lo ochal lach. *Lakurban lo ochal lach*, רבי מאיר *Rabbi
Meir* says it's forbidden, which is crazy. נן קרבן korban *Nan
kurban*—now actually it's not crazy, because why would—well, if you ignore מכלל
לאו אתה שומע הן *miklal lav attah shomea hen*, why should לקרבן
לא אוכל לך lo ochal lach, *Lakurban lo ochal lach* be אסור
assur. *assur*? לקרבן לקרבן לא אוכל לך lo ochal lach. *Lakurban, Lakurban
lo ochal lach*.
So the things that I don't eat are a non-קרבן korban,
*kurban*. Non-קרבן korban, *kurban* are your—your non-foods are non-קרבן korban, *kurban*, which
means if you don't—if you're not bothered מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן
*miklal lav attah shomea hen*, which means your foods are קרבן korban,
*kurban*, are a קרבן korban *kurban*. Your non-foods are non-קרבן korban, *kurban*,
therefore, right, your foods are—if you're don't—if you're not concerned about מכלל
לאו אתה שומע הן *miklal lav attah shomea hen*. So saying לקרבן
לא אוכל לך lo ochal lach *Lakurban lo ochal lach* is אסור
assur, *assur* for רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* is אסור assur. *assur* can
make sense if you're not bothered with רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*, okay.
What do you mean by bothered with?
If you're not following the position of רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*. If
you're not following his position, okay. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says,
וקשיא לן *v'kashlan*, and then we ask, so that's what the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*'s going to say. הא לית ליה מכלל לאו אתה שומע
הן *Ha leit lei miklal lav attah shomea hen*. How did he
get to your non-foods are non-קרבן Korban *kurban* means your foods are
קרבן Korban, *kurban*? That's a מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן *miklal lav
attah shomea hen* problem. והא לית ליה מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן
*Veha leit lei miklal lav attah shomea hen?* אימא סיפא
*Eima seifa*—I'm sorry did I skip a line? ואמר רבי אבא נעשה
כאומר לקרבן יהא לפיכך לא אוכל lo ochal, לך *V'amar Rabbi Abba,
na'aseh k'omer: Lakurban yehei, lefikach lo ochal lach*. So we read this
not as לקרבן *Lakurban*, again, what did he actually say? I don't
know. Okay, but we read it as though he said לקרבן *Lakurban*,
this thing is like a קרבן Korban, *kurban* and therefore I won't
eat it. Okay, so again, he's... I mean what does it mean
נס כעמר *nas k'omer*? This gets to Michael's question. Is it clear
that we know what he wanted to say? So since we can
fit the sentence in in a particular way to say that, you
said לקרבן *lakorban* what you really meant was לקרבן *lekorban* this should
be a קרבן Korban. *korban* therefore I won't eat it. And therefore
it's working according to Rabbi Meir. It's not a מכללא *mikhalla*. You're
just saying קונם Konam *konam*. Exactly. I won't eat this קונם Konam.
*konam*. That's how we read this. Okay. That's how that works. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. לפיכך לא אוכלך *lefikhakh lo
okhalkha*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says so that's true why not
say the same thing here? Now how would we say the same
thing here? לחולין lechullin. לא אוכלך *l'chulin lo okhalkha*. Here's how we
would say it. Is everybody with me here? Right but here it's
not the word קרבן Korban, *korban* here it's the word
חולין *chulin*. No. So here דאפי' *d'afilu* he said לקרבן *lekorban* therefore
I won't eat it. Here you know what we're going to say?
We're going to keep it לחולין lechullin *l'chulin* therefore I won't eat
it. Okay? You got it? That's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says.
If for Rabbi Meir לקרבן לא אוכלך *lekorban lo okhalkha* to make
it a meaningful sentence we're going to read it as לקרבן *lekorban*
this thing will be a קרבן Korban? *korban* therefore I won't eat
it. So certainly לחולין lachullin לא אוכלך *l'chulin lo okhalkha* just stop
at the לחולין lachullin *l'chulin*. This thing is a לחולין lichullin *l'chulin*
means קרבן Korban *korban* according to even according to Rabbi Meir right?
That's what it meant over here. So why don't we say this
is a קרבן *korban* therefore I won't eat it?
So it should be אסור assur, *assur*.
That's the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*'s question. If this is אסור assur. *assur*
because we're going to interpret it and take לא אוכלך *lo okhalkha*
as a therefore as a separate point right? So certainly this right
לחולין lachullin. *l'chulin* קרבן *korban* I
therefore I won't eat it so why is it מותר *muttar*? Alright
so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says האי תנא סבר לה כרבי מאיר
בחדא ופליג עליה בחדא *hai tanna savar lah k'Rabbi Meir b'chada u'p'lig
leh b'chada*. Alright you're right. This משנה mishnah *mishnah* ברייתא braita *braita*
holds like him in one and argues in one. סבר לה כוותיה
בחדא דלית ליה מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן *savar lah k'vatieh b'chada
d'leit leh mikhlal lav ata shomeia hen* ופליג עליה בקרבן *u'palig leh
b'korban*. So basically it says ah okay it doesn't hold of the
idea of this other of this משנה mishnah *mishnah* here that you
quoted. This holds that you don't say מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן
*mikhlal lav ata shomeia hen*. That was statement number one. So just
because you tell me my my house is חולין *chulin* does not
mean that my food is a קרבן *korban*. Okay this is the
Rabbi Meir position. But when you get down to here we don't
chop the sentence in two. We don't hold of this משנה mishnah
*mishnah* קרבן *korban* idea that you chop the sentence in two. Okay
we read this as one big thing. So reading this as one
big thing it means my car and my non-food things are הקדש
heckdesh, *hekdesh*. Okay but it doesn't basically mean you know but that
doesn't make my food אסור assur, *assur*. Okay. Yes?
So you're saying basically what we said לקרבן לא אוכלך *lekorban lo
okhalkha* what forced us to say that in order to ask the
question הכא נמי *hakha nami* and what is the answer? So הכא
נמי *hakha nami* is
is that לקרבן לא אוכלך *lekorban lo okhalkha* if לחולין lachullin *l'chulin*
means קרבן *korban* if we've just described that לחולין lachullin *l'chulin* means
קרבן *korban* right? That's what the word לחולין *l'chulin* means. So לחולין
לא אוכלך *l'chulin lo okhalkha* is the exact same as לקרבן לא
אוכלך *lekorban lo okhalkha*.
So that was the קשיא *kashya*.
That was the קשיא *kashya*.
What's the answer?
The answer is that this תנא *tanna* doesn't hold of this משנה
mishnah *mishnah*. Okay? This תנא *tanna* holds of Rabbi Meir מכלל לאו
אתה שומע הן *mikhlal lav ata shomeia hen* but it doesn't hold
that we read this sentence and we say therefore לא אוכלך *lo
okhalkha*. If we don't read it that way so לקרבן לא אוכלך
*lekorban lo okhalkha* actually would be מותר *muttar*. We don't say it's
לקרבן *lekorban* therefore לא אוכלך *lo okhalkha*. We say the things that
I don't eat are a קרבן *korban* or whatever. So fine whatever
doesn't mean anything. Here too the things that I don't eat are
a קרבן *korban*. It doesn't mean that the things that I do
eat are a קרבן *korban*.
So what's מותר *muttar* refer to what's מותר *muttar*?
All the food
everything is מותר *muttar*. If I say the things that those things
that I don't eat are a קרבן *korban* okay
it's everything else I eat
so I'm not אסור assur. *assur*-ing anything right? Right.
So it's like you're just making a I
have a piece of food in front of me I have a
piece of bread and I say that that I don't eat is
a קרבן *korban*.
I mean you haven't referred to the bread in front of you.
I guess you could wonder okay so why isn't the computer a
קרבן *korban* or something? Somehow it's clear that you're only directing your
words to this piece of bread in front of you. And since
so therefore this sentence is like a meaningless sentence.
It's not a נדר neder *neder* because it's a...
because it doesn't לא אוכלך *lo okhalkha* is not referring to the
to the bread. Now what you might want to have said now
the only way it would be is if you're saying this is
a קרבן *korban* and therefore I won't eat it. That's the language
of this משנה mishnah *mishnah*. Okay? So if that if you wanted
to say it this piece of bread in front of me is
a לחולין *l'chulin* is a קרבן *korban* and I won't eat it
which actually is a very reasonable thing to say that I mean.
If I say to this loaf of bread in front of me
קרבן לא אוכלך *korban lo okhalkha* okay so... That actually makes a
lot of sense. But since we tend to interpret the classic נדר
neder as אוכל לך, ochal lach, which doesn't mean that's what I'm
planning on doing, right? This is an important point because it keeps
on coming up, and this is why this is confusing, which is
a classic נדר neder is קונם אוכל לך, konam ochal lach, which
means, which is, wait, what do you mean, you will? You're saying
you won't eat. But we classically, since we interpret a נדר neder
as not relating to me and my action, but to the object,
the classic נדר neder, is that fact, you know, those things I
would eat of
yours are הקדש. hekdesh. So therefore you could have understood that when
you said הקדש לא אוכל לך heckdesh lo ochal lach it means
exactly what the משנה Mishna says it means: it's הקדש, hekdesh, therefore
I won't eat it. But we know we want to interpret that's
what this משנה Mishna over here had, and there, according to that
approach, it would be אסור. assur, Okay, we would say it's הקדש,
therefore I won't eat it. But we are going to, this ברייתא
braita is assuming that we're going to always interpret the words by
a נדר neder in terms of the object, not in terms of
you. This means that the first, this is referring to the object.
The object is הקדש, therefore I won't eat it. Okay, that is
a pretty logical thing to say. But the other, but this ברייתא
braita is assuming, says the גמרא, Gemara that since we're talking about
a נדר, neder. we're going to interpret everything about the object. So
this says, okay, the object is, you know, so this says, it's
הקדש, that at those things that I don't eat of yours. Okay?
So it's like, you know, so therefore you're not saying that the
food is הקדש, you're saying the non-food is הקדש or something. Okay?
So לחולין, right.
Those two sentences, לקרבן לא אוכל לך ochal lach and לחולין לא
אוכל לך ochal lach are the same sentence and the גמרא is
playing with two different ways.
It's saying that the author of this, that there's what, there's the
position of the משנה that says that's a binding sentence, and there's
the position of the ברייתא that says it's a non-binding sentence. The
question is, if you're prepared to say the second part of the
sentence is talking about me and the first part about the object,
then it's binding. If you're going to say because we're dealing with
נדרים nedarim we always have to be talking about the object, so
then the only binding sentence is when you say that food is
אסור. assur, This doesn't say that food is אסור, assur, and therefore
this refers to the object, okay, and the object is not the
food because it's the לא אוכל לך ochal lach. object, and therefore
it's not going to be אסור.
assur Yes, just a quick clarification: לא אוכל ochal לך means anything
that's not edible?
Yeah, it's not exactly clear, or it means that it could be
read that way, or it could be, you know,
let me take a look. There's a ר"ן Ran that sort of
describes what the שאני shaani and the שאיני she'eini sort of means
here.
It goes back to the first משנה about the שאני טועם, shaani
toem, if it's the שאני shaani or is it the שאיני. she'eini.
שאיני אוכל לך? she'eini ochal lach?
One minute. It's
not so clear also the
whole, yeah,
I have to see exactly how that phrase, it's not exactly a
phrase like, like, yeah, it might mean more like the abstract idea,
like the fact that I won't eat from your things, and it's
the דבר שאין בו ממש, davar she'ein bo mamash, meaning it's the
fact that I won't eat from you is considered to be קרבן
or something, but it's not actually, the דבר שיש בו ממש davar
sheyesh bo mamash would only be the שאני אוכל לך, shaani ochel
lach, those things of yours that I would eat. You're right, I'm
actually, this was a little inaccurate in certain respects to say that
the לא אוכל ochal לך is sort of saying like concrete, because
if it was concrete then why don't you say that, I don't
know, my computer is הקדש, because I'm saying, right? If this is
referring to the non-food objects, so let that just apply to the
non-food object. I've got to get back to you, that's not exactly
clear a hundred percent. Yeah, let's just finish up the גמרא. It
says, רב אשי אמר הא דאמר לחולין והא דאמר לא לחולין דמשמע
לא ליהוי לחולין אלא כקרבן. Rav Ashi amar ha damar lachullin ve-ha
damar lo lachullin demashma lo lehavy lachullin ela kekorban. So basically what
רב אשי Rav Ashi is saying is, it seems to be that
רב אשי Rav Ashi is saying is, that if you say לחולין
לא אוכל לך, so that's the same as קרבן לא אוכל לך
korban lo ochal lach and that according to the משנה would be
actually binding, because it would mean it'll be a קרבן, therefore I
won't eat it. When the משנה says that it's not a problem,
it's that you said לחולין. Okay, so therefore לחולין not a problem,
but if you said לחולין then... How you said אוכל or לא
אוכל, we would interpret this as the food is קרבן, and here
we'd say it's קרבן, therefore I won't eat it. Okay. So אביי
Abaye basically says that it is like the משנה over there. Look,
I want to say, I have to get back to you because
the ראשונים Rishonim are a little bit vague about this. It gets
back to the question of the first משנה when it says
קונם שאני אוכל. Konam she-ani ochal. Okay. Now, זבידי Z'vidi that קונם
Konam, is the food of yours that I would eat, but some
have the גרסא girsa שאיני אוכל, she-eini ochal, which is basically exactly
the same. This is אסור, assur, therefore I won't eat it. Okay.
And if you said קונם שאיני אוכל, Konam she-eini ochal, does that
work or not? There's a מחלוקת ראשונים machloket Rishonim because exactly this
point, that you might have to say שאני אוכל, she-ani ochal, which
means the food is a קונם. שאיני אוכל Konam she-eini ochal. you're
talking about what you're going to do, and therefore it's not לשון
נדר. lashon neder. Okay. So I did that once before, I ruined
a shirt. Okay. Anyway, so that is the, that's exactly this question
of when you say קרבן לא אוכל לך, korban lo ochal lach,
if it's לשון נדר, lashon neder, you know, you have to chop
it in half, that's לשון נדר, lashon neder, this is just describing...
You describe the object, that is to say... I understand, that is
to say...
That's exactly, no, not the food that, it is קונם, Konam, therefore
I won't eat it.
No, but there's another way to understand that phrase is not with
the
therefore.
That would be without the י. yud. The food that I would
eat is קונם, Konam, that's without the י. yud. With the י,
yud, it's the difference with and without the י yud is אוכל
לך or לא אוכל לך. אוכל לך is the food is אסור.
This is talking about you. Okay, that you won't eat it. So
that becomes the question when you do the I won't eat it,
is that לשון נדר lashon neder or not. Okay. So this was
confusing, and I understand how it was because I was trying to
say it's not food objects. So what? So my car should be
אסור, my computer should be אסור. But it seems to be like
that if you're willing to make it two sentences, it's אסור, therefore
I won't eat it, that's when it's saying that it's אסור, that's
that language, and שאיני אוכל she-eini ochal would also be because we
split the sentence in half. It's אסור, therefore I won't eat it.
And the approach that it's מותר, which in the end the גמרא
sort of gives up, would be sort of like you're trying to
sort of, you're sort of saying a נדר בלשון שבועה. neder bilshon
shevua. It's לחולין that I won't eat from you. You know, and
that's you're not referring to the object, you're referring to the fact
that you won't eat.
And אוכל means for you.
Well, alright, let's go on. So the גמרא says like this.
I had... Yes... I have, I have the Steinsaltz Neve of a
vowelized text of the משנה גמרא. Mishna Gemara. Yeah. Without that, I
wouldn't be able to read this at all.
Yeah. Well, that's how come the גמרא is also free to switch
the גרסא girsa from לחולין to לחולין. Yeah, and I don't know
how you're supposed to know by context. Okay. Alright, but bottom line,
the פשט pshat of all of this is that really we, this
whole thing reads like the תוספות ריד, that even within רבי מאיר,
the word לחולין means הקדש. So רבי מאיר could say this is
מותר because we don't say מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן, but we
still would say that this is אסור because לחולין means הקדש, like
the גמרא here thought, לחולין לא אוכל לך is the same as
לקרבן לא אוכל לך. So that's point number one. And point number
two is when you actually say קרבן לא אוכל לך, korban lo
ochal lach, which is, is that like... that's very reasonable. This is
a קרבן, I won't eat it. Okay, so the first part is
basically לשון נדר, lashon neder, the second part is like descriptive. And
according to that, we would say that it, that it works. But
however, and that's sort of like קונם Konam, שאיני אוכל. she-eini ochal
This is a קונם, Konam? I.E. I'm not going to eat from
it. Okay, and the second part is descriptive. But the other approach
is to say no, it's not a נדר because you're saying, you
know, it's a קרבן that I won't eat from it, which is
doesn't relate to an object. You have to relate to an object.
And what you're saying is the non-eating from it somehow is a
קרבן, and that's actually not a meaningful statement. Okay, so that's the
question of the שאני שאיני, she-ani she-eini, the לא אוכל לך as
opposed to אוכל לך. Okay, let's go
on. I knew it was going to take the whole hour. טהור
וטמא נותר ופיגול. Tahor v'tamai notar u'pigul. You know, it's funny because
I was looking at this once, I've got like if you'd look
at this on Bar Ilan, right, the entire amount of words of
this like whole דף daf is like four sentences or something, but
it's like it takes so long to get to. Okay. Anyway, טהור
וטמא נותר ופיגול אסור. Tahor v'tamai notar u'pigul assur. בעי רמי בר
חמא. Ba'ei Rami bar Chama. הרי עלי כבשר זבחי שלמים לאחר זריקת
דמים מהו.
Harei alai k'vasar zivchei shelamim
le-achar zrikat damim mahu. If somebody says this piece of bread is
forbidden to me like the meat of a שלמים shelamim after its
the blood has been thrown on the מזבח, mizbeiach, which is because
and when the meat becomes מותר to be eaten, what's the status?
So the גמרא says what do you mean? מהו. mahu. אי דקאמר
בהדין
לישנא,
Ee dikamar
behadein lishna,
says the
גמרא, if you said explicitly that language, בהיתירא קמתפיס. be-heteira kamatpis.
You're allowed to eat that meat, so what are you? So it
might be a דבר הנדור, davar hanadur, but it's a דבר המותר.
davar hamutar. So the גמרא says אלא כגון דמחית בשר זבחי שלמים,
Ella kegon demachit basar zivchei shelamim, that you have in front of
you, you have the meat of a שלמים shelamim after the blood.
It's been sprinkled? So there you are in ירושלים Yerushalayim eating your
שלמים, Shelamim, chomping away, and ומנח דאתי גבי u-manach d'atei gabei and
then somebody put a piece of bread in front of you ואמר
זה כזה. ve-amar ze ke-ze. This piece of bread is like this
meat that I'm eating, please pass the mustard. So מאי, mai, what
do we say? בעיקרו קמתפיס או בהיתר קמתפיס?
Be-ikaro ka-matpis o
be-heiter ka-matpis? When you say it's like this, it's like this leg
of lamb that I'm eating right here, do you mean the original
identity of this leg of lamb, of this thing which was a
קרבן before? It originated as a קרבן שלמים Korban Shelamim before זריקת
דמים. zrikas damim. A קרבן שלמים Korban Shelamim when it was alive,
right, or whatever, you couldn't derive benefit from it until you had
זריקת דמים, zrikas damim, right, it's the throwing of the blood, the
offering of the sacrifice that allows me to eat the meat. Right.
So when you're saying it should be like this leg of lamb
here, do you mean like this originally was and this way is
like saying קונם, Konam is that a כינוי Kinuy for קרבן, like
this? Okay? Like this? Do I mean קונם? If קונם means קרבן,
then this means קרבן. Or do you say בעיקרו קמתפיס או בהיתר
קמתפיס? Be-ikaro ka-matpis o be-heiter ka-matpis? Or you are being מתפיס, matpis,
מתפיס matpis is an important word to introduce here, will come up
a lot, to grab it. Okay? To be מתפיס, matpis, but means
it's like you're taking that concept, you're grabbing onto it with this
other, you
know, what point are you saying it then? What? You know you're
going to eat it anyway.
Michael, we're back to the point that it doesn't matter what you
meant, it matters what you said. Okay? So how are we prepared
to interpret it? It's not a question of what you mean. Are
we prepared to interpret it in terms of the original identity of
this thing and a כינוי Kinuy for קרבן, or do we say
no, you're relating to this as it is right now and this
is not a דבר הנדור, Davar ha-Nadur, or certainly not a דבר
הנדור Davar ha-Nadur that's אסור, and therefore it was not a לשון
lashon of, it wasn't a כינוי, Kinuy, it was not a לשון
of נדר. Okay.
I understand but you said אחר זריקת דמים, achar zrikas damim, so
he must mean, no,
but he didn't say the words, that's what I want to say,
he didn't say the words אחר זריקת דמים, achar zrikas damim, he's
holding up the leg of lamb of the שלמים Shelamim that he's
eating and he's saying this piece of bread should be like this.
Okay? What do you mean like this? Is this your way of
saying should be like a קרבן?
Or is this your way
of...
alright... no, it's not changing the words.
הרי עלי כ... Harai alai ke...
it depends where you put the end quote. Fine, what do you
want me to say, the גמרא always does it, it depends where
you put the end quote. It means somebody says הרי עלי, harai
alai, not the words that are coming are not like a בשר
זבחי שלמים אחר זריקה. basar zivchei Shelamim achar zrika. He said הרי
עלי harai alai like an object that was בשר זבחי שלמים אחר
זריקה. basar zivchei Shelamim achar zrika. Okay? That's how it's read.
So put the quote
at the end of עלי? alai? Yeah, somebody said הרי עלי כ
harai alai ke this object that's in front of me which happened
to have been an object that was בשר זבחי שלמים אחר שחיטה.
basar zivchei Shelamim achar sh'chita. So what do we say? בעיקרו קמתפיס
או בהיתירא... Be-ikaro ka-matpis o be-heitera... מתפיס matpis means you're grabbing it.
Are you sort of taking that as the model and applying to
it that identity of you know the of what its original identity
was which was the קרבן or is it its current status as
something מותר? Okay and it's already 8:30 so we will have to
leave you at that cliffhanger for tomorrow.
I have a question. What's la-yogurt? What?
You said
la-yogurt. La-yogurt, alright, very funny, right, exactly.
When do we first get...